hi welcome back to the loan rim
we're on episode 13. i call it uh
it might set the sky a fire
it might set the sky a fire and
just to get us into the mood of this
episode
uh i'd like to show a picture this is a
this is actually the first uh detonation
of a nuclear weapon
uh in this world this was in
near the end of world war ii and uh
actually this bomb was exploded not far
from here
i i have driven there before it's a few
hours drive from where i'm speaking
in new mexico in the united states
and these scientists
including fermi and and earlier einstein
and oppenheimer who worked at princeton
uh they believed it was theoretically
possible to create a
nuclear reaction
and it would create a large bomb and uh
and they talked the president united
states into this project
uh to make this bomb and
when they had it ready in theory they
took it to new mexico
uh near here and they
set it off in the morning when they out
in the desert
uh the project was called trinity just
sort of meaning like a powerful dandy
uh and i read some amazing conversations
with the scientists and the military
people
and uh the military people said is this
safe you know
if if we explode this bomb
could something happen that we don't
know about
and the scientists were like no no uh
you know we'll make enough
uh explosion to destroy a city for
example
uh so don't don't worry about it you
know we we unders
we we got it under control and then uh
this one scientist raised his hand and i
i just
somebody should make a movie about it he
he raised his hand and he said there's a
small
chance of a problem and uh this military
guys are like what
and he said well we don't quite know
but there's a there is some chance that
it will ignite
the whole atmosphere of earth and it
will destroy
everything on earth and all the people
on earth there's a chance
that the reaction will go through the
oxygen of the entire earth
you know and they're like okay just a
chance right
yeah just a chance you know damn let's
go ahead with it you know
so as i whenever i read that i was like
wow you know here's this they're trying
to do a little bomb
and uh it could go wrong you see
it it could destroy everything
okay and and that's the theme of this
episode 13 all right let's read the
tibetan together
so now they're talking about
disastrous results of
diamond wave practice if we don't have
this
attitude of trying to help having made a
commitment to help everyone
okay uh then this is a story oh this
says
it's like the story of the brahmana
youth called chanakya uh which we talked
about earlier so i went back and got it
for you
and the the text earlier in the lamrim
uh day 13. it says trump
not he got
magical powers by practicing
tantra and then he misused them
and he he actually killed uh
a number of people with the powers that
he gained through the practice of the
secret teachings
so here it says then he went to the
lowest of the hill realms
so we're talking about you know before
we had the example of someone who
didn't use the power of tantra correctly
and all that happened was they saw
emptiness directly
and now we're talking about other people
who didn't have this bodhichitta
motivation and when they practiced
tantra it got worse
it was like the whole sky blew up you
know it's like
they ended up in the hell realms because
they were doing these powerful practices
uh without this motivation to help all
living beings
okay all right there are three stories
[Music]
put
then there's a story of a yogi
tantrika in india who was uh
practicing yamari in tibetan it's called
shinji
it's similar to yamantaka and uh
he was reborn as a spirit as
a as a negative spirit a bad spirit and
these spirits tend to wander into other
places
so he actually wandered up towards tibet
and he reached tibet
and atisha became aware of the spirit
and kind of like a made a deal with him
where he offered him a torma and
and then chased him off okay so part te
pa
torma chine partepa means
lord atisha gave him a torma offering
and then he chased him off he said now
you should go okay
so this is again a disaster result
from practicing the higher teachings
without this without this commitment
to these to these beings third story
here
this again is a story that was told
before pembo is an area
of tibet i think it's north of plaza
okay i'm not sure i've i've known some
monks from there
uh jj king nailed jobashik there was a
tantrika practicing yamataka and uh
he was born yidam ki suk
this is a weird word okay i should offer
seiji a hundred dollars
you ready uh or
tim yidak
okay you duck you know uh
a pretty right what a yidam
yeah yeah attentive daily
sukchan
he was born okay cancel the bet
he was born into the form of what
he was born as a predator but he looked
like
yamada a very weird karma okay if i just
dumped her
uh without a high motivation he was
constantly thinking about this fierce
danny
and he died and he was reborn as a
praetor but the pray don't look like the
fierce deity that's
that's all he got that was his result of
his tempting practice okay
then some of his friends who had done
the yamari retreat with him
were offering a dorma to the local
spirits and he showed up
yeah and they were like hey are you
you're my sister
i'm your old friend you know and i i
tried to practice tantra
without this motivation so all i got was
i looked like him but i live like a
praetor i'm suffering
terribly okay we it'd be weird to meet
your retreat friends
later you know and they look at you and
they say oh
your mind is here and you say no i'm not
your mother i'm just a plain old penta
you know
please give me some torma you know
please leave me torments more frequently
okay
you don't want to go to diamond mountain
on a retreat
practice in practice medicine get the
medicine
buddha initiation online okay and do the
retreat online
at home and then you die
and you become a ghost
uh that looks like medicine but it'd be
weird right and then your friends are
offering tormas and you show up
it's a weird story okay we don't want to
do that okay
then nowadays
if peltier means most people uh
if they see a tantric daily in person
yi donkey shall seek shell seek means if
they see the face
of the tempting danny that they're
praying to
or they gain some kind of ability to
read other people's minds
or they can fly in the sky or they know
people
who say i met tara in person
or you know i can read i can read what
you're thinking
or you know i can fly in the sky and
then people are like
wow your practice is awesome you know
you must have a really good buddhist
practice if you can see deities
and you can read people's minds and you
can fly in the sky and then
pablo chase says
yeah that's cool but if you don't have
bodhichitta you could go to hell because
of those three
you know they could take you to hell
seeing danny
flying in the sky reading other people's
minds if you do it for the wrong reason
it could take you to the hell realms
okay if you don't have bodhichitta
okay then i'm going to do
so it doesn't really help you and me if
we can read other people's minds
or we can do little magic tricks uh
okay pen me talk means it doesn't help
us that much
uh samdi yuna ni
shan chin lang matsukum but if you
get this experience where you meet
other beings directly and make a
commitment to them
to keep to for their happiness take the
champion
then you really reached the essence of
dharma you have the essence of dharma
inside of you
forget meeting tantric deities forget
having the ability to read other
people's minds if you just have
this kind of love from a personal bond
with each
being and a commitment to them to help
them
to take care of them as if you were
their parent
then that's that's really the core of
the dharma okay
uh take tender give me your assembly you
make it jason draw
whether or not we can call you on
someone who's practicing the bodhisattva
way
only depends on this experience okay
it it it's the crux of the whole
question
is have you met beings have you made
this commitment to them or at least are
you aspiring to that
yeah then we can say you're on the
bodies off the track or not okay
these by the way you can have the
it can be that you haven't had that
experience directly but you
strongly attracted to it that's fine
so the next picture here
uh is a picture it's a cute picture
uh where's the of a bird
and uh this it's a lady and she's
feeding a bird
and this is a practice that i used to do
with my former partner christy
and and it was a very sweet practice and
uh we used to go to mcdonald's the only
thing we could eat at mcdonald's was
french fries
and uh we had read this part of the lam
rim
and we would take uh
little pieces of french fries so you
know the story of the tigress
when lord buddha in his former life
was a prince called i think his name was
big big courage mr courage
and he went into the jungle and he found
a
tigress who was dying of hunger
and had four babies who were trying to
nurse from her but couldn't she couldn't
produce milk
and you know to make a long story short
he
offers her his body
he offers the five his body if they make
you know with a commitment that they
should be his first five students
and they were caldenya and four others
so there's this act of truth you can do
by feeding another being okay and
so we used to go to mcdonald's order the
french fries break them up into little
pieces
and then we would feed the bird the
sparrows
who come to the mcdonald's you know and
we would make a prayer you know if you
eat my french fry
then you're going to be reborn as my
student when i become a buddha
so then it becomes very cool to go to
mcdonald's otherwise it's kind of weird
to go to mcdonald's right
but so actually he mentions it here
tundra senchachi jimbatsundang if you
have
this kind of motivation and you go to a
mcdonald's and you feed
pieces of french fries to the little
birds there
even activities which are karmically
flat okay they have no great karmic
power okay giving french fries to a bird
or going to the toilet in the mcdonald's
okay
karmically neutral activities it's
called here uh
neutral activities not i mean
giving the french fries to the birds is
a little bit good karma
let's say you you go in and you want to
use the toilet so you buy some french
fries sometimes i do that
uh even the going to the toilet
which by definition is almost karmically
neutral not good not bad
i guess it depends on how bad a bomb you
make
uh but uh
it's correctly neutral it becomes a
great virtue
okay giving the he says
uh sun here means uh jimba sin means
on down to giving french fries to a bird
on
down to giving french fries to a bird
or even going to the toilet at
mcdonald's
something neutral becomes a high
bodhisattva act
that's awesome you know that's awesome
if we can have this
background motivation all the time that
i would like to i would like
to i would like to
as a parent save every living being if
you think like that
then all the little stuff you do
brushing your teeth you know
cleaning your house it all becomes the
high karma so everything you do becomes
some kind of supercharged karma
you don't have any neutral actions
anymore everything you do is
supercharged that's very cool okay all
right
um zhongchang tope
and all of those actions cleaning your
house brushing your teeth
going to the bathroom at mcdonald's
feeding the birds
they all become direct causes for
buddhahood okay
very cool
now this is a very controversial
statement
i don't want you to hear it
and then everybody's like oh tell me uh
changes
50 sanskrit
huh
kenta mahatma okay mahatma
this is the tibetan from mahatma and it
means a great being
it means a great being okay uh like
mahatma gandhi
uh chang sen means those bodhisattva
mahatmas okay
uh i don't know let's think of something
yeah okay you go to mcdonald's
uh you want to give french fries to the
birds
as a bodhisattva activity and
then you find out you don't have any
money or credit card
uh and you go outside and there's a guy
sitting next to you eating french fries
okay
and he looks away
and you swipe a french fry and you
give it to the birth okay
under special circumstances
if your motivation is high enough
that stealing a french fry
becomes a good karma okay
because of the motivation okay and
that's an extremely
dangerous idea okay and i was trying to
think of some picture
that i could show you
that would demonstrate how dangerous
this idea is so i got this
picture of a fugal fish in japan
okay and a fugal fish is also called a
blowfish
and there are parts of
inside this fish that are highly highly
poisonous
they are more poisonous than cyanide
okay and uh so i don't know there's this
i don't know japanese cool people
and i spend time working in japan
there's this thing of
courage thing bravery thing they said
give me a
they go to the restaurant and say give
me a fuga fish and the guy's like but
you know if you eat the wrong piece you
will die
here now with the fish in your mouth
you will die that fast you know and and
i looked it up
50 people died in japan every year from
frugal fish
they're like i'm gonna try you know and
supposed to be
it's super delicious because it's so
dangerous
so uh and and to cook it legally
you have to have three years of training
you have to have a license and you have
to have three years of training to to
legally serve it in a restaurant
to cook it most of people who die buy
one and take it home and try to do it
themselves
but uh so you know what i'm talking
about right
you got what i'm talking about right uh
to steal the french fry
and give it to the birth takes a very
skilled
highly trained bodhisattva
and if if you and me try it we will just
end up on the floor
dead uh with fugal fish in our mouth
okay so uh
you know there's a if there's a
there's a joke that no matter how many
times you tell a student something's
dangerous someone's going to try it
anyway
uh so please don't okay
he's just trying to make a point that uh
things that are normally not nice
these high high bodies dagnin chambo
means not just a normal bodhisattva but
a very high body suffer
it's possible they could steal a french
fry
and what do you call it turn it over
into an incredible
good deed but it's extremely rare
like eating food fish okay so don't be a
fool
fool all right
[Music]
okay
uh in general uh
seeing emptiness directly okay tony toke
showed up here
uh if you can see emptiness directly
tapas tsum gay chang chuki ger
jo okay so this chang tube here
does not mean chanchu simba it does not
mean bodhisattva it means buddhahood but
it doesn't mean buddhahood
it means enlightenment of the three
kinds
okay of the three vehicles of the three
tracks
and there are two lower tracks if you
get to the end of them because you saw
emptiness directly
without bodhichitta then those
do create nirvana but it's called lower
nirvana and we already talked about how
we don't want to go there okay
uh
but seeing emptiness directly
has that power even for a person
who doesn't have a high motivation so
even for a person
who does not have a high motivation
seeing emptiness directly
can give birth inside of them to nirvana
and therefore is called ma
it's called the mother yum like yabyum
okay it's called the mother so here it's
ma
and i'd like to go to the next picture
which i negotiated
very with great difficulty from a family
in in sedona okay
and here you see aaron chad
mrs nick lashaw you see nick lascha
and you see their baby emily okay so
just imagine uh amelie
uh being a buddha which is not difficult
looking at her face
and the the mother
of the buddhas the aaron of all buddhas
is the direct perception emptiness okay
so we can say
that seeing emptiness directly is the
mother of the buddha like aaron for
emily okay
uh chang semni lame chandrakone
[Music]
only has one result you can't go on the
three tracks
after having that experience once you've
had that experience
the two lower tracks are cancelled you
are restricted
to the highest track and the highest
track the body stop attract
always ends in total buddhahood complete
buddhahood okay
uh la may means uh
highest totally highest okay
incomparable
nothing higher what okay so konig
so really it's like a father okay so if
we go back to the photo
uh so nick
nick represents the uh bodhichitta
okay nick represents buddhism
and the mom there's something here i
mean you guys got to think about it in
your study groups maybe there's some
kind of statement here i don't know
exactly what it is
the emptiness realization could go three
ways
you could become a complete buddha or
you could just reach nirvana so
therefore it's like a mother
but the bodhichitta can only go to
full enlightenment therefore it's like a
father so maybe it's some statement
about
what a mother is and what a father is i
don't know
uh you have to you guys can debate it in
your
in your discussion groups okay he's
making some kind of statement like that
uh giveaway pad you know
youngster and by the way he makes a a
side this is an assad he's making a side
statement he says
there by the way that's why we call the
perfection of wisdom
as in yabyum okay you means holy mother
or something like that
that's why we call the perfection of
wisdom holy
mother i looked up what you mean is in
sanskrit
and it took me a while oftentimes it's
simply
prajnaparamita the perfectionist but
sometimes it's called mata
which means mother okay then
indian people call their moms mataji
so yum in tibetan
referring to the direct perception
emptiness and the literature
that helps you get there the mother
sutra
or the mother the great mother okay
all right and together they're called
mata pitta
or
sometimes amba for the for the mom or
sometimes pitter matar
okay which means father and mother okay
all right last part here tonight
this is an interesting statement
okay uh there's a word here and the
second line
called took thundi till to dumb detail
at the end of the second line here
yeah and till means uh the palm of your
hand
this is lock till this is
kang till okay the palm of your foot the
sole of your foot okay
uh and uh lacteal means uh
you know so i gotta i got a piece of gum
here okay and uh
if you hold out your hand and
you you put it in the middle of your
hand okay that's called
uh lock till and and it means
what's your one most important buddhist
practice
it's called what's in the palm of your
hand it's kind of funny
by the way the name of the book is not
liberation in the palm of your hand
the name of the book is a gift of
liberation
shoved into your open hands
thank you i wasn't expecting that
but this poem it means
look what's the one practice
you should always have at hand in your
hands
what's your one lock
tuk dum ki till means uh what is your
private number one practice okay what is
your number one
dharma theme for your whole life you
know which have you selected
is it vagina practice or i don't know is
it death meditation
or is it seeing emptiness directly
what's what's the one thing you want to
be buried with
you know what's the one thing you want
in your hand okay
saggy gopashi now first he excludes a
certain group of people
okay first he excludes a certain group
of people
he says look i'm not talking about
people
who don't want to become a buddha okay
so
forget those people it's really funny
i don't know why he said that you know
he says look
what i'm about to say it's just meant
for you guys who want to become a buddha
you know so
if you don't want to become a buddha
then don't listen to this next part okay
he said he says that he said
if if you're not interested and become
buddha you don't have to listen to this
part okay
but if you are interested in being a
buddha
then there's only one you know
practice you should devote your whole
life to the one practice you keep in the
palm of your hand
and that you gotta have this experience
where you meet you know every single
being
one by one and commit to
you commit to help them overcome
all pain you know you make that personal
connection and commitment to every
single living being
bugs fish birds martians
people living on the other side of the
universe all of them
uh in a single meditation okay so
let's let's make that the one thing
you're gonna work on for the rest of
your life
let this be your heart practice okay all
right
till the jaw takes take some and soaked
like butch
this pardena okay uh
very very unusual word you won't see it
very often
day means to chase an animal while
you're hunting it
okay it's got a weird it's a weird word
you know
like you're hunting a rabbit and you
keep running out to the rabbit you know
and that's called date
and uh pad day is an idiom in tibetan
and it means uh boils down to you know
if you chase chase chase chase it all
comes down to this what
he says look all of buddhism
the whole buddhist practice 300 000 john
brady
books you know
all buddhist practice ultimately
pardena if it boils down to
trying to get this experience trying to
have this experience
with every living being all buddhist
practice
thousands and thousands of books you
know
thousands of hours of meditation it all
boils down to
can you trigger this experience can you
have this experience yourself
okay very cool all right
see you in the next episode thank you
you